Friends, whenever insurance is mentioned, the
word third party is heard the most,
but information about it
is quite limited because we often take first party
claims, that is, the claims for getting our vehicle repaired, but
because it is
very difficult to take a third party claim and at the same time,
a claim is taken in rare cases from a very big claim, so the
information related to it is quite limited and that is
why it becomes very important to have information about it.
So friends, in today's
video we will learn what a third party
insurance policy is, why it is
important, how much amount of claim can we
take in it and the entire process of taking a claim.
If someone has
filed a third party claim against you, I will also go through that process
and if you have to
file a third party claim against someone, then
we will learn about that process also in this video.
Hello friends, my name is Harvinder Singh
and I welcome you to the
YouTube channel of DSC Solutions. Through this channel,
our effort is to
spread as much awareness as possible about insurance so that
any related matter can be solved.  The process is whether to
buy a policy, to get a claim service done or
whatever else you need, so that you do
not have any doubts related to it and you do not face any
problem in it. If you also
want to join our efforts or you agree with these things of ours, then
you can subscribe to the channel
and do
not forget to share the information wherever necessary. So start the video.
Third party, as you can see from the name itself that
it has a third number, so
who is the first and second party. Suppose you have a
car or a bike and you have
also got it insured, then in this case
you are the first party, that is, the owner of the vehicle,
he is the first party
and the insurance company which has insured your vehicle is the
second party and the third
party is all those people or properties or
vehicles which can be at risk from your vehicle, they can
get damaged at some time or the other. So,
third party insurance policy is that policy
which compensates the loss caused to the other person,
for example, if there is a property,
a vehicle or a person gets injured, then the person
who will settle their claim is under a third
party insurance policy. So
friends, now let us talk about third party
insurance policy.  Why is it necessary?
Under the Motor Vehicle Act, if you
drive any bike or any vehicle on the road, then
you must have at least a third party policy because see, whether you get the
coverage of your vehicle
or not, but whoever can get harmed by your vehicle
or is at risk, it is
your responsibility to cover their risk, so at least the third party
policy which is legal liability policy, we
can get it, it is mandatory for you to have it and
if you want to cover the damage to your vehicle as
well, then you
can take a first party policy, in which both these
damages will be covered, of your vehicle as well
and if someone in front gets harmed, then that will
also be covered in it, now
friends let's talk about how much amount of
claim can be received under the third party policy,
see, there are two types of damages in it
which can reach anyone from our side,
which is the first category, in that if any damage is caused to any vehicle, any
property, any thing which is
not alive, that is, inanimate objects, then
that thing will come in the first category and secondly if
If our car collides with a person and
he gets seriously injured or he does
not survive, then there can be two types of losses. So, in the
first
category, if our car collides with any vehicle or
property, then
if this loss is caused by your vehicle, that is, if
this loss is caused by tax, then the
limit of claim in third party is Rs 7.5
lakh and if any loss is caused by a bike or a two-
wheeler, then the
limit of third party claim is Rs 1 lakh
and in the second category of loss, if
a person gets seriously injured or does
not survive, then the amount of claim is
decided by the court. It will
depend on their loss of income,
how much money the injured person earns, what
was his income, on that basis a code
will decide how much claim amount he should get.
Now friends, let us talk about the
process of third party claim. Now see,
because the process is very difficult and is
used only in very big clamps. Let
us see the third party
policy.  What is
written in it and what are the formalities,
that is a different thing, we will talk about the
facts which are
actually true, which are ground reality,
after that we will talk, suppose I am
driving a car and
my car collides with another car, then the first
reaction is that both the parties will
talk among themselves, there will be a debate or it will be decided
whose fault it is and if that loss is a
minor loss of 5-10 thousand,
then we will try to solve it on the spot itself
and the
party whose fault it is
gives the repair cost to the other party on the spot itself, this is the reason behind this
because the process of processing third party claim is very
complicated and difficult, it goes through your police
station and court and
because the vehicles which sometimes have an accident with each other are
not necessarily
local and from the same city, hence it is not convenient for them to take such
trouble, so if there is a minor loss, then they
settle the matter there itself,
which  The party at fault bears the
repair cost. But
in other cases, suppose the loss is
huge, someone is seriously injured, someone
dies, or the vehicle is severely
damaged, the repair cost will be
very high. So, what is the procedure for that? First of all,
if
we have to file a third party claim against someone, then for that, first of all,
you will have to
register it at the nearest police station
and also get it registered with Akhil.
After that, we will contact a
motor insurance claim lawyer, that is, a
lawyer who deals with such cases
because the case will go to court.
See, the civil courts do
not handle motor accident cases, so
your case will go to the Motor Insurance Claim
Tribunal and then there the court
will decide, after looking at all the facts and all the
documents, which party was at
fault. So friends, now let's talk about
how much claim the court will give us in this.
First of all, if a person gets injured and does
not survive, then in the case,
his loss of income, that is, how much income did he have?  The
court will decide the damage caused and accordingly,
how much claim the insurance company has to pay. Secondly,
if you want to claim the repairs of your vehicle
from the insurance company under a third party claim, then for that,
you will have to present all your vehicle repair
invoices, survey reports or any
related documents before the court.
Only after looking at all of that, the court will arrive at a specific amount
and you and the insurance
company will have to agree to that amount. Now
friends, we have just discussed the process of if we file a
third party claim against someone.
Now friends, let's
talk about if someone else files a third
party claim against us,
what is the process of that.
See, in that, we have to do only one small thing
that we do not have to be guilty proof
that at the time of the accident, the
mistake which they are trying to prove was
not our fault, then what will happen in that,
that the insurance company will have to pay this entire claim,
so how do we protect ourselves
from being guilty proof?  You can save yourself by presenting
all the documents of your vehicle at the time of the
accident,
such as your vehicle's RC,
insurance, valid insurance,
pollution certificate, and
driving license. All these
documents will have to be presented in the court. Along with
this, you should not violate any major traffic rules, that is, you are
not driving under the influence of any intoxication, you are not
driving under the influence of alcohol,
you are not driving on the wrong side,
you are not driving with more passengers than the seating capacity, or you are
not carrying any illegal goods in the vehicle.
If you prove both these things in the court
that all your
documents are complete and you are
not violating any traffic rules, then the
entire liability and the
responsibility of paying the claim gets transferred to your insurance company.
Then you have no
role in it. The court
will decide the amount and your insurance company will pay the
claim to them. This is your only role as the
first party.  You have to prove
that you have
all the valid documents of your vehicle and also that you are
not breaking any major rules. Now
friends, because third party
claims are very technical, there can be
different scenarios,
different cases and it is
not possible for me to discuss all the cases
in one video. If you have
any different question related to any claim, in which there is
some different situation, then you
can definitely ask us in the comment section. Friends,
I have just given you information about this third party. I
explained the entire process of claim in the entire video, so I hope
you have understood this information
and it will definitely be useful to you somewhere.
If you like the information, then do
not forget to subscribe to the channel for feedback.
And if you have any suggestion, if
you want to change anything in the content of the video or want to give your advice, then
you can also send that in the comment section.
Along with this, if
you want a video made on any specific topic
about which  If you
want any information, please let us know by writing in the comment section.
So friends, I will
meet you next week. Till then,
take care of yourself, stay happy and stay healthy. Thank
you
[Music]